Why has TSMC
become one of the most important companies in the world?
This tiny chip brought TSMC
2.16 trillion NT dollars in annual revenue
accounted for nearly 10%
of Taiwan’s GDP in 2023
In July 2024, TSMC’s market capitalization of surpassed 1 trillion NT dollars
making it the world’s second-largest semiconductor company
just behind Nvidia
The semiconductor industry isn’t just competition between companies
but can impact economy and national defense of a country
The most intensive game in modern tech
and even in politics & economics
is called the “chip war”
Why is TSMC so important
and why is it founded in Taiwan?
We have to shift our perspective
let this tiny chip answer the question
Why the third industrial revolution
begin with this nanometer-sizes technology
Remember how the semiconductor industry rose?
In 1959, Robert Noyce invented the mesa-structure IC
and two years earlier, in 1957
Jay Lathrop developed photolithography tech
The two inventions
meant the birth of “Chips”
and established the foundation for mass production
hence started the chip era
10 years later, in 1968
Noyce and Gordon Moore left Fairchild Semiconductor
to establish Intel, focusing on memory chips
logic chips
and personal computers
This fueled the rapid growth of the semiconductor industry
But in 1968
something very important to Taiwan happened
To assess whether Taiwan
was ready for setting up factories
Texas Instruments (TI) sent two heavyweight figures
to meet with Taiwan’s Minister of Economic Affairs, Li Kwoh-ting
These gentlemen were
Mark Shepherd Jr., who would become TI’s CEO the following year
and Morris Chang
After this meeting
Li Kwoh-ting spent the next 17 years
persuading Morris Chang to move to Taiwan
Looking back, this long-term recruitment mission
proved to be invaluable
You could say Li Kwoh-ting had remarkable foresight
he recognized that transistors and semiconductors
were industries Taiwan had to invest in
But why on earth are transistors so important
and why does demand for semiconductor production capacity
get larger year by year?
In the AI era
we all know only by aiming for more powerful computers
models with greater processing power
lower time costs
and the ability to identify, compute and generate
can we beat competitors in the market
It sounds complicated
yet it can be simply put
For we need only two numbers 0 and 1
to store and precess all data
with digital information
If we only need to represent 0 and 1
then even electric lights can do that
Let a lit lightbulb represent 1
and an unlit one represent 0
then a series of lit or unlit lightbulbs
can form a sequence of data
such as Morse code
Of course, computers are not just on/off lights
They can run AI models
to do all kinds of computing
because they know how to “think”
which means “logical operations”
To make a computer think
doesn’t mean giving it a biological brain
like a human or any other intelligent lifeform
In fact even the large generative language models
like GPT
when you break them down
there’s a supercomputer powering them
What consist of this supercomputer
are countless tiny processors
At their core, the smallest units
are vast numbers of tiny logic gates
But what is a logic gate?
It’s like a tiny switch that operates based on rules
If we increase the number of switches controlling the lightbulb
from a single switch to two
and insert a “logit gate” in the middle
you can play lots of tricks
For example, we can design an “AND” gate
to apply limit to the device
Only if both gates are open will the lightbulb shine
If we replace it with an “OR” gate
then either switched on will let lightbulb shine
If you like something special
then you can use a “XOR” gate
It lights up only when one switch is on and the other is off
Let’s do a quick recap
Logic gates aren’t exclusive to transistors
We talked about how in 1937, before transistors existed
Math genius Claude Shannon
built a switching circuit with relays
that could do complex logic computing
At first glance, logic gates seem to only handle simple sorting tasks
but these tiny units have evolved from simple switches
to cores that can do basic logic operations
If I rearrange these components
to combine an AND gate with an XOR gate
I create the simplest half adder
that can calculate 0 + 0 = 0
1 + 0 = 1
0 + 1 = 1
You might think, “Anyone can do this in their head!”
Why do we need a computer for this?
Hold on, take a step further
If we combine two half-adders,
and add four AND gates for permutation
we get a simple binary multiplier
that can multiply numbers from 0×0 to 3×3
From simple logical operations, we progressed to addition
and then multiplication
and so on
By combining enough logic gates in different arrangements
we can perform division, square roots, and even calculus
and various mathematical calculations
Furthermore
Computers consists of these math operation units
can execute virtually any task you can imagine
Of course, we’re skipping a lot of details here
But one major issue is:
we can’t possibly design a new circuit
for every single mathematical operation
For example, a dedicated circuit for squaring numbers
or cubing numbers
So, how to design a computer
that can handle any kind of task?
This ties back to what we discussed earlier
about the Von Neumann model and Harvard architecture
No time to elaborate now
If you’d like to dive deeper
leave a comment on the PanSci website
Now, back to our question
We know anything can be done with logic gates
but why can these gadgets
perform logical decision-making?
Could there be a tiny alien operator
hiding inside?
Well, inside every logic gate is a transistor
We’ve covered the principle of transistors earlier
It’s called ”triode”,the predecessor of vacuum tube
It works like a tiny water valve
Using minor current to control whether a larger current can pass through
If you forgot, that’s all right
review it after watching this episode
To sum up, a transistor is like a tiny water valve
It stays closed when there’s no input voltage
and opens when voltage is applied
What happens if we connect two transistors together?
you’ll find out
only when both water valves are open at the same time
can the water flow through
This forms an AND gate
Of course, other logic gates can be more complex
For example, a XOR gate looks like this
and so forth
Transistors can build up all the logic gates
and logic gates can accomplish all calculations
So transistors are the core of a CPU’s logic circuits
Nowadays
whether it’s building faster CPUs
or designing multi-core processors
for parallel multitasking
we rely on increasing the number of transistors
or developing newer, smaller chip structure
In fact, since the founding of Intel
the world’s demand for computing power has only continued to grow
till now, the race for more computing power
shows no signs of slowing down
As the third industrial revolution swept across the globe
TSMC became one of its biggest beneficiaries
bringing Taiwan onto the global stage
Why was TSMC founded in Taiwan
instead of somewhere else?
From TSMC, Taiwan’s "Guardian Tech Giant,"
to the entire Taiwanese semiconductor industry
which forms the so-called “sillicon shield”
there are three key figures you must know
They are Sun Yun-suan
Li Kwoh-ting and Morris Chang
Sun Yun-suan and Li Kwoh-ting
both served as Taiwan’s Minister of Economic Affairs in the 1960s
and were instrumental in shaping Taiwan’s economic and technological development
Sun Yun-suan was the first director of TaiPower company in 1946
where he spearheaded efforts to rebuild Taiwan’s power grid
This laid the foundation for Taiwan’s economic  development
He also founded the Industrial Technology Research Institute (ITRI) in 1973
Moreover, in the 1970s,
while Taiwan was promoting its Ten Major Construction Projects,
he, along with Li Kwoh-ting and former National Tsing Hua University President Shu Shien-Siu,
pushed for the establishment of Hsinchu Science Park.
Every one of these initiatives had a far-reaching impact on Taiwan’s economy
When it comes to the establishment of ITRI and HSP
Li Kwoh-ting also deserves a share of credit
Yet Li’s another important credit
was persuading Morris Chang to come to Taiwan
The 17-year-long recruitment effort
left a lasting impression on Morris Chang
In November 2023, the Li Kwoh-ting Foundation
presented the first LKT Award to
none other than Morris Chang
In his speech, Morris Chang stated
Without LKT, there would be no TSMC
According to Morris Chang’s memoir
he had three key encounters with LKT
Firstly, after the initial meeting in 1968
From then until 1980
LKT made almost yearly trips to
Texas Instruments (TI), where Morris Chang was working
tirelessly urging him to come to Taiwan
He even took him to see the construction of Hsinchu Science Park
hoping to convince him to relocate
The second encounter was in 1980, after the passing
of TI chairman Patrick Haggerty
LKT reached out  again in 1982
inviting Chang to become the director of ITRI in Taiwan
After careful consideration, Chang declined
He recalled LKT’s frustration in his reply letter
which read
Why would you turn down such a great opportunity?
The third and final time, Chang was finally persuaded
and moved to Tawan to take up the position of ITRI director in 1985
Just three weeks into the role
LKT approached him with the idea of establishing a semiconductor company—TSMC
He also convinced the government to invest in TSMC
Morris Chang later elaborated
“The idea of founding TSMC and its business model
was mine
but executing the plan and
convincing the government to fund 50% of it
was entirely LKT’s doing
The business model Chang referred to
was the pure-play foundry model
He foresaw that
fabless semiconductor companies would rise
leading to a more specialized semiconductor industry
Companies focused solely on chip design would appear
while semiconductor foundries would grow into a massive market
Morris Chang structured TSMC to focus solely on production, without designing chips
maintaining a “collaborative” rather than a “competitive” relationship
with other companies
This strategy set the stage
for what we’ll discuss in the next episode—
the ongoing battle between TSMC and Samsung
The impact of this strategy will become clear
Fast forward to the 2000s
the landscape of semiconductor manufacturing in Asia
are largely
a competition between TSMC and Samsung
Samsung was no easy competitor
Since Apple’s first-generation iPhone chips
the choice was Samsung instead of TSMC
As transistors continued to shrink
approaching the 20-nanometer node
We found that further miniaturization became increasingly difficult
Any smaller transistor brings leakage
and higher power consumption
Logic gates become invalid too
Faced with this challenge
how did TSMC respond?
And who will carry forward Moore’s Law?
In the next episode
We’re entering the world of 3D transistors
and witness the Taiwan-Korea semiconductor battle
explore the true reason behind Taiwan’s dominance in the semiconductor industry
Stay tuned to our channel
See you next time